John Orr Young Papers
John Orr Young Papers
1907-1965
Young, John Orr, 1886-
3.0 linear feet
Papers of the American advertising executive. Includes manuscript of an article; published material by Young; correspondence, 1951-1952; and personal miscellany.
148777
Biographical History
Born June 25, 1886 in Leon, Iowa to John Lewis Young and his wife, John Orr Young was an American advertising executive and consultant. From 1906 to 1908 he studied at Lake Forest College in Lake Forest, Illinois, and then began his career in the advertising department of the Salt Lake Herald Tribune in Salt Lake City, Utah. From 1910 to 1912 he was the advertising manager of the Chicago firm of Lord & Thomas, and in 1913 he became advertising manager of Crisco, a division of Procter & Gamble.
In 1921 he and Raymond Rubicam, a fellow advertising consultant, founded the advertising agency Young and Rubicam. The agency's clients and products eventually included notable names such as General Foods (Postum, Grape Nuts, Jell-O), Gulf Oil, Parket Cavis (drugs), General Electric (radios), Arrow (shirts and collars), Travelers Insurance, International Silver, Jell-O, Borden's (dairy products), Johnson's baby powder, Swan soap, Four Roses Whisky, and Metropolitan Life.
From 1921-1935 Young retired from business life, but in 1937 he took a job as consultant for W.P.B. in Washington, DC and then in 1945 opened his own business, John Orr Young Associates, for which he served as consultant and president.
Young was a member of the Union Club and the Phi Pi Epsilon fraternity at Lake Forest. He is the author of Adventures in Advertising (1949).
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The John Orr Young Papers consist of two accessions which have not been integrated.
1967 accession
The 1967 accession is divided into manuscripts and published material. Manuscripts contains a single article by Young, while Published material contains two articles by Young and a number of newsletter-pamphlets.
1978 accession
The 1978 accession is divided into three parts. Personal miscellany includes news clippings, photographs, and yearbooks. Advertising business contains newsletters, posters, awards, and a manuscript by Young. 1952 Eisenhower campaign includes correspondence, news clippings, and a scrapbookand includes letters
Arrangement of the Collection
Note that because the two accessions have not been integrated, box numbers are not unique. Please specify accession and box number when requesting material.
Subject and Genre Headings
Business and Industry; Young, John Orr, 1886-; Rubicam & Young.; Advertising agencies -- United States.; Manuscripts (document genre); Photoprints.; Correspondence.; Advertising.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Inventory
- Manuscripts (1966 accession)
  - "Hogs to Hoboken" (by Young), undated (Box 1)
- Published material (1966 accession)
  - Articles by
    - "Pick an Advertising Agency," Dunn's Review, undated (Box 1)
    - "Adventures in Advertising," Printer's Ink, 1948 (Box 1)
  - Newspaper letters by
    - The Town Crier, 1961 (Box 1)
  - Pamphlets by
    - Agency Management, no's 1-39, undated; 3 folders (Box 1)
    - Better Advertising, no's 40-80, 83, 86-97 and unidentified pages, undated; 7 folders (Box 1)
- Personal miscellany (1978 accession)
  - News clippings, 1949-1961 (Box 1)
  - Photographs, 1940-1960 (Box 1)
  - Photographs (oversize), 1940-1960 (Oversize 1)
  - Yearbooks, 1908; 1910; 2 volumes (Box 1)
  - Yearbooks, 1907-1908; 1 volume (Box 2)
- Advertising business (1978 accession)
  - Adventures in Advertising, by John Orr Young, 1 volume (Box 2)
  - "Better Advertising Newsletter", 1953-1965; 1 volume (Box 2)
  - Posters: advertisements, 1929-1940 (Oversize 1)
  - Booklet: ad campaign, 1925 (Oversize 1)
  - Award: advertising, 1950 (Oversize 1)
- Eisenhower campaign (1978 accession)
  - Correspondence, 1951-1952; 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1951-1952; 1 volume (Box 2)
  - Scrapbook of news clippings, 1947-1952; 1 volume (Oversize 1)